We've had exclusive early access to the brand new Google Alpha Evolve paper,
which just got released one minute ago.
We did a technical interview with the authors before anyone else.
The paper itself drops a bombshell,
setting world records for many algorithmic and mathematical challenges.
In the world of computer science,
few problems are as fundamental as matrix multiplication.
For over half a century, a specific efficiency benchmark in this domain,
particularly for 4x4 matrices, seemed insurmountable.
The search base for optimal algorithms is immense,
making exhaustive exploration practically impossible,
even for relatively small matrices.
In 1969, Volker Strassen revolutionized the field
by discovering an algorithm to multiply two 2x2 matrices
using only seven scalar multiplications, down from the standard eight.
The established best practice for larger matrices, like 4x4s,
was to apply Strassen's 2x2 method recursively.
For 4x4 matrices, this meant seven times seven,
resulting in 49 scalar multiplications.
Today, Alpha Evolve beat this record.
Google DeepMind has a long history of building AI systems
which actually invent new knowledge through experimentation and iteration,
rather than just building a glorified database.
We saw AlphaGo, which beat Lisa Dole,
learning from human games and even surpassing champions through self-play.
AlphaZero was purely self-play,
and AlphaFold predicted millions of 3D protein structures
that had never been measured experimentally,
and AlphaDev discovered faster sorting algorithms.
Google DeepMind recently has been focused on scientific discovery
with AlphaTensor, which framed the problem of finding
faster matrix multiplication algorithms as a game.
Achieving breakthroughs and FunSearch took us even further,
using large language models to find new mathematical solutions
by evolving code.
And now, Alpha Evolve represents the next stage in this lineage.
For the usual case of matrices that have arbitrary numbers in them,
still nothing better was known than doing Strassen twice
using 49 multiplications.
So, we were really excited when we used Alpha Evolve in this setting.
We actually didn't even hope that it would find something better than 49,
because we were trying for so long with AlphaTensor.
We just ran it for completeness, because we wanted to have this table
in the paper that we actually have, that we tried on all the sizes
up to five or six, and remarkably, it found a faster algorithm,
which uses 48 instead of 49 multiplications.
It's a bit like cursor on steroids.
It iteratively refines algorithms, drawing on the creative power of LLMs,
using meta-learning, library learning, automated evaluation,
and evolutionary search.
The Alpha Evolve paper describes it as an evolutionary coding agent,
which substantially enhances capabilities of pre-trained
LLM models on difficult tasks.
Of course, their first paper was FunSearch, which was very, very similar.
The main difference, I think, was that it was just
searching for a single function rather than Alpha Evolve,
which can essentially work over an entire codebase.
You just demarcate adaptable regions in a codebase,
and it can search for those.
Of course, it's even optimizing for interactions
between those functions in different parts of your codebase.
One potential issue, as Keith Duggar pointed out,
is the classic halting problem in computer science.
But there's also a really subtle limitation here
I want to explore with you guys a bit,
which is running the programs themselves.
We face issues, right?
You face issues of the halting problem, for one thing.
Like, you start running some code,
like the code compiles fine or doesn't crash immediately,
and it starts running, but maybe some time goes by, like an hour.
And you're like, well, geez, is this thing ever going to terminate?
In theory, you're of course right.
You can never tell that if you run an algorithm for longer what it would have done.
But in practice, it actually hasn't been any sort of issue for us
in the applications that we looked at.
Alexander Novikov added that this challenge is very much like
a fundamental aspect of human research too.
How do you know that you should stop working on your problem as a human?
Or maybe you spend a month more and then you solve it, right?
It's hard.
I mean, of course, there's still limitations.
They didn't bite much on my halting problem limitation.
So in practice, it was okay for them,
but they had these very well-chosen problems, right?
We're like, okay, matrix multiplication.
You know, if it's any slower than Strassen's algorithm,
maybe you can turn it off.
But the problem is that that restricts your open-ended search capabilities, right?
You can't go down the path of a potentially slower algorithm for now
that may get you to a stepping stone that hops you over to something more efficient.
It is interesting, isn't it?
There's so many breakthroughs in science are unknown unknowns.
We might have a nose for what is interesting,
but we never really know where to find the answers.
And so often it's the case that we find them through sheer luck.
But there must be at least one step we can take in the direction of mechanizing
and accelerating this process.
In the case of matrix multiplication and several other scientific problems
which had a clear evaluation function,
this new evolutionary approach achieved much
which decades of human research could not.
We just ran it for completeness because we wanted to have this,
this table in the paper that we actually have that we tried on all the sizes
up to up to five or six.
And remarkably, it found a faster algorithm
which uses 48 instead of 49 multiplications.
Yeah, when one of my teammates messaged on the channel
that, oh, it seems like we have this result, I just couldn't believe it.
Like, let's triple check it.
AI's growing ability to generate entirely new,
provably correct algorithms can advance the frontier of science.
And the really cool thing is that AlphaEvolve has already been applied
to optimize mission-critical real-world systems within Google.
They're able to speed up really already heavily optimized pieces
of important computational infrastructure within Google.
For instance, take Google's massive data centers.
Efficiently scheduling computing jobs is a really complex operation.
If done suboptimally, expensive servers will sit around idling.
The Google engineers placed a candidate solution into AlphaEvolve
and then evolved a smarter heuristic
which assigned jobs to machines much more efficiently.
They said, post-deployment measurements across Google's fleet
confirmed the simulator's results,
revealing that this remarkably simple yet effective function
continuously recovers on average 0.7% of Google's fleet-wide compute resources
which would have otherwise been stranded.
Now, that's a huge saving on Google's scale, right?
And in another instance of self-improvement,
it even found ways to accelerate the training of the very Gemini models
which powers AlphaEvolve itself.
We have found a way to speed up the training of the next version of Gemini by 1%
and we've been able to unstrand resources in the board data center.
This instance was also interesting because it didn't generate the solutions
but also the programs which generated them.
Whenever you look at the index in the for loop,
you just look at the index module of four.
And when you index into the array,
you're indexing at position i and i plus four and i plus eight,
like, okay, what's going on?
And just by inspecting the code, we actually were able to develop,
you can think of it as like a mathematical insight
or a mathematical hypothesis.
And that hypothesis turned out to be really crucial
for then improving the result.
A key aspect of AlphaEvolve's sophistication
lies in its flexible approach to representing the search problem.
The arms will propose you like a broad range of things
and some of them will be stupid,
some of them will be amazing, some of them will be like really weird.
And then by having the ability, you can filter for those
and identify the ones that are actually kind of important
and improving things.
So isn't it really cool that rather than trying to generate the solution itself,
AlphaEvolve can just like Inception generate the thing
which generates the solution.
We should play some Inception music in the background.
The thing we found really interesting about AlphaEvolve
is that it's still very much a humans in the loop thing.
Humans identify what's interesting,
they find problems that have clear evaluators,
they place candidate solutions in the loop,
and then AlphaEvolve will traverse this cone of possibilities
and make jumps along the way, and then the cycle continues.
So this is very much sketching a future of AI
where there is a strong collaborative loop between humans and AIs.
And we should just bring in how you modeled this representation.
So you had these different approaches,
you could directly model the solution,
you could model a constructor function,
so you're actually learning a function which itself constructs the solution,
you could be learning a search algorithm
which is what you did with the matrix multiplication,
and you also spoke about coevolution as a possibility.
So many people are talking about this vision of AIs
which can autonomously just drive cars or just do anything,
generate content without any supervision from humans.
And that hasn't really panned out to be honest.
And certainly a lot of the content on the internet is slop.
Do you remember that dead internet theory by IlluminatiPirate,
this guy on an internet forum a couple of years ago?
He said that by now most content on the internet will be generated by AI
and it will have a kind of superficiality to it.
And he was right.
But it doesn't necessarily mean that AI is bad, right?
What's missing is that we need to have this exchange.
We need to use AIs as tools and we need to guide them
and refine the results and do the process iteratively.
That's kind of what AlphaRevolve does.
It mechanizes the correct way of using AI.
The thing that makes AlphaRevolve so cool and powerful
is this kind of this mech-and-forbidden humans and machines, right?
And like the humans ask questions,
the system gives you some form of the answer
and then you improve your intuition,
you improve your question-asking ability, right?
And you ask more questions.
I gave this talk a few times about generation AI
and the big warning I gave is just the rise of mediocrity.
We're just going to be inundated and flooded with mediocrity
and the best content will still be produced by the most skilled people.
And all that's going to happen is as this tide of mediocrity
grows larger and larger,
people will get hungrier and hungrier for the cream,
for the things that are rising to the top, right?
So I think all that's going to happen in the end
is that skilled people, their productivity is going to just rise
and they'll continue to be differentiated
from the mediocre sort of hordes whose productivity is also enabled.
So the hordes become more productive and experts become more productive
and just as a whole, we all become more productive.
And while we're on the subject of amazing innovative architectures
for discrete program synthesis and reasoning and whatnot,
why don't you consider applying to work at Two for AI Labs?
That's if you're an ML research scientist or ML engineer.
Benjamin Kruzier is running the lab.
It's in Zurich at the moment
and they're thinking about opening an office in San Francisco as well.
They would love for you to get in contact with them
and apply if you're interested in working for them.
So give Benjamin a shout.
Guys, welcome to MLST.
It's an honor to have you both here.
Thank you for having us.